Finding Aid to the Neal McCoy papers CA.MS.00342
Smith College Archives
Neal McCoy papers
1921-2001
Smith College Archives
McCoy, Neal, 1905-2001
CA.MS.00342
4.583 linear feet (11 containers)
Neal McCoy was a professor of mathematics. The papers contain correspondence, course materials, photographs, programs for awards, publications, and the diaries of his wife Ardis Hollingsworth McCoy.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Neal McCoy papers were donated to the Smith College Archives from a number of sources.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into four series:
Series I: Biographical Information
Series II: Correspondence
Series III. Teaching and Other Work
Series IV. Ardis Hollingsworth McCoy
Biographical / Historical
Neal Henry McCoy was born on March 6, 1905 in the Oklahoma Territory. He received his A.B. from Baylor University, then his M.S. and Ph.D. degrees from the University of Iowa. He joined the Smith College mathematics department in 1931 after two years as a National Research Fellow in Mathematics at Princeton University. His son Paul was killed in a car accident in 1957 at the age of 22. While at Smith, McCoy spent time as a visiting professor at the University of Michigan, University of Wisconsin, and University of North Carolina, and taught at the National Science Foundation Institute for secondary school math teachers. He was known as a professor who loved to teach and focused on the students. He wrote six undergraduate textbooks including Introduction to Modern Algebra, which has been translated into many foreign languages. His other books include An Introduction to Mathematical Analysis, The Theory of Rings, and The Theory of Numbers. He was also active in the Northampton community. He served on the Board of Directors of the Northampton YMCA, and worked for United Way. His primary research interest was abstract algebra. McCoy was the first male member of the Smith mathematics department. He co-founded the Connecticut Valley Mathematics Colloquium in 1938. He edited the Duke Mathematical Journal from 1951-1954, and was a member of the American Mathematical Society, the Mathematical Association of America, and the Association of Teachers of Mathematics in New England. In 1963, he was appointed to the position of Gates Chair in Mathematics at Smith. Professor McCoy retired in 1970 and lived with his wife, Ardis Hollingsworth McCoy, in Northampton until his death on January 4, 2001 at the age of 95.
Scope and Contents
The Neal McCoy papers contain correspondence, course materials, the diaries of his wife Ardis Hollingsworth McCoy, photographs, publications, programs for awards ceremonies, and information about McCoy's career at Smith. The bulk of the collection consists of personal and professional correspondence-primarily from McCoy's years at Smith-and reprints of McCoy's mathematical publications.
McCoy, Neal, 1905-2001
- Series I: Biographical Information
  - Biographical Material, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Transcripts: Bayla University and The State University of Iowa, 1921-29 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Smith College Awards Programs, "Who's Who at Smith College 1964-1965", 1934-1970; undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Obituaries and Memorial Programs, 2001; undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1932-1995 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Photographs, 1925-1968 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Smith College Charis Medal, academic pins (see artifacts) (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Series II: Correspondence
  - A, 1940-1994 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Allyn and Bacon, Inc. (publisher), 1972-1975 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Allyn and Bacon, Inc. (publisher), 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Allyn and Bacon, Inc. (publisher), 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Allyn and Bacon, Inc. (publisher), 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Amritsur, S., 1951-1955 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Aydin, Seyfettin, 1973-1981 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - B, 1944-1979; undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Birkhoff, Garrett, 1955-1973 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - C, 1943-1982; undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Chacron, M, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Chawla, L.M., 1968-1979 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Ching, Wai-Sin, 1976-1978 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Chittim, Richard, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Cope, Jane, 1968-1973 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Copeland, Arthur, 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Curtis, Morton, 1962-1965 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - D, 1941-1980 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Dickinson, Alice, 1961-1971 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Divinsky, Nathan, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - E, 1963-1972; undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - F, 1925-2000; undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Fuchs, L., 1959-1967; undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - G, 1929-1974 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Gehman, Harry, 1948-1968 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Gemignani, Michael, 1971-1980 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Gilmer, Robert, 1968-1972 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Gonzales, Brother, 1965-1970 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - H, 1942-1978 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Hsu, John, 1970-1973; undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Hsu, Ying Fen, 1971-1974; undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Hutchinson, Joan, 1969-1975; undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - I, 1941-1967; undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - J, 1955-1999 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Jain, S.K., 1962-1965; undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Johnson, Dick, 1937-1977 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Jones, Burton, 1954-1967 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - K, 1938-1978 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Kertesz, Andre, 1955-1974 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - L, 1934-1987; undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Langer, Rudolf E., 1941-1949 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Ma-Mc, 1944-1989; undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - MacLane, Saunders, 1945-1975 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - McBrien, Vincento, 1960-1976 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - McDonald, Florence, 1953-1975 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Me-My, 1948-1977 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Mendelson, Bert and Marion, 1963-1972; undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Mendenhall, Thomas, 1959-1970 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Mookini, Edwin, 1965-1968 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Moore, Richard, 1972-1978 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - N, 1945-1975 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Nash, Robert D., 1965-1967 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - O, 1937-1973; undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - P, 1941-1982; undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Q-R, 1937-1979 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Rinehart & Company (publisher), 1955-1965 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Rolf, Howard L., 1970-1979; undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Rosenbaum, Robert A., 1962-1978 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Sa-Sk, 1938-1980 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Sankaran, Y., 1961-1966 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Sm-Sz, 1939-1974; undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Steinfeld, Otto, 1965-1974 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Szasz, Ferenc Andor, 1960-1976; undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Szele, Tibor, 1951-1954 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - T, 1937-1981; undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Tripathi, S.M., 1977-1984; undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Tsai, Yeong-Shyeong, 1969; undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - U-V, 1937-1972 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Van der Walt, Andres P.J., 1956-1965; undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Vaughn, Randal L., 1973-1974; undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Wa-Wi, 1943-1971 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Whidden, Helen L., 1968-1970 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Willcox, A.B., 1969-1973 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Wo-Wr, 1966-1983 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Y-Z, 1964-1979 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Zenkteler, Leon, 1956-1957 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Fundamentals of Abstract Algebra, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Fundamentals of Abstract Algebra, 1971-1972 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Fundamentals of Abstract Algebra (Opinion Form Letters), 1972 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Fundamentals of College Mathematics Revisions, 1958-1964 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Introduction to Modern Algebra, 1957-1959 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Introduction to Modern Algebra, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Introduction to Modern Algebra, 1961-1966 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Introduction to Modern Algebra, 1966-1973 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Introduction to Modern Algebra (Opinion Form Letters), 1960 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Introduction to Modern Algebra (2) (Opinion Form Letters), 1960 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Introduction to Modern Algebra (3) (Opinion Form Letters), 1960-1961 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Introduction to Modern Algebra (Opinion Form Letters), 1975 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - The Theory of Numbers, 1962-1966 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - The Theory of Rings (originally Elements of Ring Theory), 1962-1967 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - The Theory of Rings, 1971-1972 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - The Theory of Rings, 1973-1983 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Publications, General, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Publications, General, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Publications, General, 1976-1977 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Unidentified, 1936-1978; undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Series III. Teaching and Other Work
  - Smith College Math Department: Notes and Memoranda, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Smith College Math Department: Notes and Memoranda, 1958-1959 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Smith College Math Department: Meeting Minutes and Memoranda, 1977-1978 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Smith College Math Department: Meeting Minutes and Memoranda, 1979-1981 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Mathematical Association of America: Mailing Lists and Correspondence, 1958-June 1959 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Mathematical Association of America: Mailing Lists and Correspondence, July-December 1959 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Mathematical Association of America: program Presentation of Awards; Memoranda, 1994; undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Mathematical Notes: Classes and Lectures, 1967-1968 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Mathematical Notes: Classes and Lectures, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Mathematical Notes: Group Theory, 1968-1972; undated (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Mathematical Notes: The Goldie Theorems, undated (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Mathematical Notes: Annihilator Ideals in Semi-Prime Rings, undated (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous Notes for Presentations and Papers, undated (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - National Science Foundation Programs: General, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - National Science Foundation Programs: General, 1962-1964 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - National Science Foundation Programs: General, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - National Science Foundation Programs: General, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - National Science Foundation Programs: General, 1967-1969 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Summer Institute: Theory of Rings, Madison, 1953 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Summer Institute for Teachers of High School Mathematics: Introduction to Modern Algebra: National Science Foundation: Iowa City, 1957 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Summer Institute for Teachers of High School Mathematics: Introduction to Modern Algebra: National Science Foundation: Iowa City, 1959 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Summer Institutes for Teachers of High School Mathematics: National Science Foundation, General, 1959-1960 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Summer Institutes for Teachers of High School Mathematics: National Science Foundation, General, 1960-1961 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Summer Institutes for Teachers of High School Mathematics: Theory of Numbers: National Science Foundation: Bowdoin, 1966 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Teaching: Math S.I. 170: UMass Final Exam, 1959 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Teaching: Math 296: The Theory of Rings, 1959 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Teaching: Math 399, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Teaching: Mount Holyoke College, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Teaching: General, 1970s (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Connecticut Valley Mathematical Colloquium, 1938-1970 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Introduction to Modern Algebra: Notes, Drafts, 1960; undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Introduction to Modern Algebra: Reviews, 1962-1963 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Journal Articles: Reprints, 1929-1936 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Journal Articles: Reprints, 1937-1950 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Journal Articles: Reprints, 1950-1983; undated (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - List of Publications, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 9)
- Series IV. Ardis Hollingsworth McCoy
  - Diaries, 1960-1962 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Diaries, 1963-1965 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Diaries, 1966-1968 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Diaries, 1969-1971 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Diaries, 1972-1974 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Diaries, 1975-1977 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Diaries, 1978-1980 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Diaries, 1981-1983 (Box 11, Folder 4)